Hello, I'm Brian Cox.
I'm Robert Ince, and this is the Infinite Monkey Cage.
Now, all of you, and I imagine there's been a few daydreamers here,
when you stare out of the window at school, that's what they say.
Concentrate! What are you doing staring out of the window?
Well, for some people, it wasn't just daydreaming.
It was practising to become a meteorologist or a cloud expert.
Or an astronomer, I suppose.
Or an astronomer. What time did you go to school?
LAUGHTER
I'm from Oldham.
Oh, what? From Oldham, the sky, we're at...
It's always dark, dark, with industrial plumes.
You've not bought your clogs again, have you?
Cos they made a right racket last time.
I couldn't wear them standing on those volcanoes looking enigmatic,
could I? Cos the clicking would spoil the...
Oh, they're not made for going over overcooled lava, are they?
No. Oh, OK.
They're made of wood. It's the worst possible thing to wear,
to be honest, walking through lava, isn't it?
Isn't it? There must be something... Well, paper, I suppose.
LAUGHTER
Oh, no. Oh, cos we only had paper shoes in Oldham. Yeah, whatever.
Anyway, today we're looking to the sky,
but not as far as Brian likes to look.
It's a kind of parochial level of looking to the sky.
We're going to go, well, really, the level of clouds.
The clouds that, of course, so often hindered your series' stargazing.
Why were there always clouds there? Was it Dara O Briain's head?
Because I think because of the roundness of the head,
they might have attracted clouds closer.
LAUGHTER
Today we're asking, how do clouds help
in maintaining... I can't say maintaining.
I'll do it if you want. Here we go. You do it.
Today we're asking, how do clouds help in maintaining a healthy atmosphere?
What can clouds, which are so beautiful and so wonderful,
and sometimes they shine with ice crystals,
what can they teach us about the climate?
Now you've got to do my line, doing me.
LAUGHTER
To guide us through!
That's Bernard Mann, isn't it?
Oh, you can tell that.
To guide us through, we're joined by a climate scientist.
Don't worry, it's all right. The show's going to be OK.
LAUGHTER
To guide us through, we're joined by a climate scientist,
a cloud appreciator and, well, a drummer.
Oh, but so much more than a drummer.
And they are.
My name's Gavin Predepinney, I'm member number one
and the founder of the Cloud Appreciation Society,
which I started 20 years ago,
and it brings people together from all around the world,
120 countries we've got members in, all united in the belief that,
well, clouds aren't something to complain about,
they're actually one of the most evocative and dynamic
and maybe you could say poetic aspects of nature.
And the most wonderful thing I've seen in a morning sky
is a morning glory.
LAUGHTER
Which you'll be relieved...
No!
LAUGHTER
It is a cloud formation that forms in a remote part
of northern Queensland in Australia.
It's a cloud that glider pilots surf,
just like surfers on an ocean wave.
It travels across the Gulf of Carpentaria through the night
and it arrives first thing in the morning on the Queensland coast.
And I went there and I watched this cloud arrive,
I rushed up into a plane with all the other gliders
and watched them as they surfed up and down this cloud
as the sunrise was breaking over the top of it.
It was an absolutely glorious and beautiful sight.
Hello, I'm Amanda Maycock.
I'm an atmospheric scientist and a professor from the University of Leeds.
I use computer models to simulate the movement of the air
within the Earth's atmosphere, including clouds,
and how it affects the Earth's climate.
The most wonderful thing I saw in this morning's sky,
there weren't many clouds around up in Leeds today,
was actually Venus, which is visible at the moment.
And Venus is another beautiful cloudy planet,
but a bit less hospitable than Earth
because the clouds are made of sulfuric acid
and they've contributed to a runaway greenhouse effect
that means the surface temperature is more than 450 degrees Celsius.
So that was the beautiful thing I saw this morning.
Don't worry, you'll have those sulfuric acids before you know it.
They're working really hard in the US and also...
LAUGHTER
I'm Owein Wyn Evans. I used to be a weather presenter.
Now I am a TV and radio presenter and I'm also a drummer.
I got the name the Drumming Weatherman
when I played the drums to the BBC News music in lockdown.
It went viral and then I went on to play the drums for 24 hours
for a Children in Need drum-a-thon.
Whilst every so often also doing the weather.
LAUGHTER
My husband was thrilled to have the drum kit out of the house for 24 hours.
I was thrilled to throw the drum kit into a skip after the drum-a-thon.
And the most wonderful thing that I've seen in a morning sky
is a gigantic pepper pig balloon.
Stay with me on this one.
I live in Penarth, which is near the water in South Wales.
And me and Aaron were going for a walk one morning
and saw this kind of orb over the water.
I thought, Aaron, what's that?
Aaron, that looks like pepper pig.
It was a daddy pig actually.
As the balloon approached it was indeed pepper pig.
It was drifting up the coast towards Swansea.
Stranger things have drifted up the coast towards Swansea.
It turned out to be a child's balloon
which was somehow amplified and expanded by the view across the sea.
Pepper pig drifted towards us and off she went.
Last seen off the coast of Barry.
As I think a lot of hopes and dreams have.
So there we go.
And this is our panel.
Gavin, we should start with you.
Why did you feel a cloud appreciation society was so important?
It's because people do like to complain about them a bit.
You don't need like a sort of kitten appreciation society
because everyone loves them.
You need something that's a society that has a kind of mission
to shift people's perspective about the sky.
At least that's what I felt.
So really I just felt someone needed to stand up for clouds basically.
Let's get this out of the way. What's your favourite formation?
It could be a pileus.
Fair enough, that's a very strong answer.
LAUGHTER
Amanda, we need to move back to the science.
That's not science!
Move back to the science.
We had a man talking about a pepper pig balloon moment ago.
We've got to bring him gently back to the science.
I'm just saying, what's your favourite cloud?
I said favourite formation, Brian.
Is there a technical difference between the...
Have I made a terrible mistake?
Formation is just a general term
because basically they're all clouds.
They're these random appearances in the sky.
But humans are amazing at spotting patterns.
And so when we started to classify clouds in a scientific way,
1802, around then,
and it was actually an Englishman called Luke Howard,
a Quaker from Tottenham,
he was spotting patterns and he started to give them Latin names.
So he came up with the cumulus and cirrus and stratus.
And these names just basically say what the clouds look like.
And you say it in Latin, sounds fancy, makes it sound scientific.
See, Brian, you put too much effort in learning physics.
Amanda, how do clouds, at the most basic level, how do clouds form?
So a cloud forms when a parcel of air becomes saturated
and some of the moisture that it contains condenses.
So where does that come from, the moisture in the air?
Well, if you imagine standing and drawing a sort of square around your feet
that was sort of one metre squared
and you weighed all of the water above your head,
there's on average about 25 kilograms of water
all the way up to the top of the atmosphere,
which doesn't sound like a lot,
it's certainly a lot less than the rest of the mass of the air,
but it is enough to form these clouds.
So basically the evaporation mainly comes from over the oceans,
we've got the vast oceans that provide that source.
And the sun heats the surface of the earth,
the air warms up, warm air rises,
it moves up through the atmosphere
and as it does so it cools and it expands.
And it's that expansion and cooling
that can cause the air to become saturated
and that's the point at which the cloud droplets can begin to form.
But they don't just form by themselves,
they need something to cling on to, as it were,
and they tend to form around little things you can't see,
specks in the air, they might be bits of dust,
bits of pollen, fungal spores from trees
and the water molecules condense around those little particles
and start to grow a droplet.
And then where does the structure come from?
Because we've heard that there are,
how many, is there a number for how many different types
of classified cloud formations?
Yeah, well, there are 10 basic types,
the genera, the main types,
and those are the ones you'll have heard of at school,
cumulus cirrostratus, cumulonimbus,
the superstar, you know, the storm cloud
that produces thunder and lightning and hail.
But then there are lots of these additional ones
which are sometimes just a feature
that looks just like a curl, like a tiny breaking wave,
which would be called a fluctus cloud feature.
There's a whole bunch of them.
I think there's about, when you combine them all,
it's probably about 80, something like that.
And one of them actually came
from the Cloud Appreciation Society.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah, one of the official types.
So what is giving the clouds
these different characteristics, broadly speaking?
So there's two main sort of types of particle
that we can find within clouds.
There's liquid water droplets
and then there are ice crystals.
And so a lot of the appearance
and the differences in appearance
come from how much liquid water they contain
or how much ice crystals they contain.
So the high altitude ice clouds, where it's very cold,
they have this kind of wispy appearance.
They get sort of stretched out by the winds.
So the winds are obviously blowing the clouds around.
You can often see that on a windy day.
You'll see them being blown along.
The lower altitude clouds,
which are made from liquid water,
the sort of fluffy cumulus type clouds,
they're sort of formed
because of the liquid water within them.
So, Owen, what about for you?
I know technically you'd be called a weather forecaster,
but you weren't actually forecasting weather, was you?
Yeah, that's right, yeah.
I came from a background of journalism.
When I joined BBC Weather,
the Met Office were providing the sort of data, if you like.
So I was trained up by them
and then later studied through the Open University,
meteorology through a couple of modules,
just because I think we love the weather here in the UK.
It's the first point of conversation for a lot of people.
If you don't know what to say,
it's lovely outside, it's terrible, isn't it?
Not always that camp, by the way, terrible weather.
But I think that for me,
the clouds are the things that a lot of people,
it's that thing that you can see.
And I remember when I was doing the weather in lockdown,
there was nothing to talk about
because people weren't really going out.
So the producers would give me three minutes
to fill on the weather.
Hans, everyone's inside.
But people would then start to see,
like you were saying earlier, Gavin,
about the clouds, you start to see shapes or faces.
And I think that's what's amazing about clouds.
It almost gives people a little bit of creativity,
especially cumulus clouds, the fluffy cotton wool ones.
What about, Gavin was saying about
that there's a negative attitude towards clouds.
I imagine when you were mainly doing the kind of,
the presenting the weather,
you would get letters of complaint
as if you yourself had created the weather.
I mean, did you get that?
Oh, I still do.
I've under the weather for three years
and people still say, oh, didn't forecast this, did you?
So, well, hon, if I forecast this three years ago,
I'd be monetizing this skill somehow.
It would happen a lot when we get,
we would get bad weather as well.
You know, if there were really bad storms
and we'd get weather warnings,
the yellow warning is the lowest,
then it goes up to amber warning,
which is my drug name as well.
I do think where the presenters are a bit too apologetic,
they sort of seem to feel that
and they feel a bit guilty when they say, you know,
there's going to be a lot of cloud around
in an apologetic tone.
I would like to hear a bit more detail
about what cloud is going to be around.
I'd like to know how the formations
are going to be changing through the afternoon.
I'd like to know what sort of shapes we're going to be seeing.
I would like some more detail and a bit more positivity.
I'd love that. I'd love that.
We could do like a kind of a,
what shapes will we see today in the clouds?
Like a little bet, maybe.
Did you used to send to the,
because they only used to have one shape of magnet
for the cloud, didn't they?
Whatever, whether it was a stormy cloud, whatever.
It was sort of a bit of a sad day
when they stopped using those magnets.
But I mean, that is the cumulus cloud,
the one that's in the cartoon.
And it's like the sort of generic cloud, the cumulus.
If you close your eyes and think of a cloud,
it's one of these puffy white cumuluses
that form on a sunny day.
They feel the most solid.
The word cloud comes from the old English word clod,
which means a rock or a boulder.
It's where we get the clod of earth, that term from.
These feel like solid things, cumulus clouds.
Do you know what I mean?
And that's why I think they're kind of iconic for us.
They have very, very distinctive shapes
and the edge of them is very well-defined,
which seems counterintuitive.
It's just this phenomenon where water is condensing.
So why do they have such a well-defined shape?
So it's often because of,
there's a sort of barrier of the air to be mixed
from within the cloud to the surrounding cloud.
So there's differences in temperature,
differences in density between different air masses
that are nearby each other.
So that's what provides this kind of
rather crisp looking shape often.
The base of the cloud will be where the kind of
layer of the atmosphere starts to become saturated.
I mentioned before the saturation
is a sort of necessary condition.
So again, that's something that will have
a sort of well-defined base to it.
And then at the top of the cloud,
you'll move into drier air, warmer air above,
but they're not sort of stationary things.
What's actually happening in reality
is that there's constant evaporation
and condensation occurring at the base of the cloud.
So the base of the cloud,
the little droplets will be continuously evaporating.
And then at the top of the cloud,
there'll be condensing and reforming.
So they're very sort of dynamic structures.
So is that, because I sometimes,
I do find it fascinating when you're looking
on a day where the wind is moving a cloud
and you look at that cloud and you think
it has remained in that shape and yet,
so actually within what appears to be
that kind of the stationary nature of the shape itself,
there is still all manner of movement going on there.
Yeah, absolutely.
There's a lot of motion that's happening within the clouds.
In fact, that's one of the reasons
why a cloud doesn't just fall out of the sky.
So a typical cumulus cloud,
the ones we're talking about might weigh
somewhere between about 250 or 400 tons,
something like a sort of typical 747 aircraft,
something like that.
There's a lovely gasp over there.
People are slightly more scared of clouds than they used to be.
What if they fall?
Chicken licking?
How big would that be?
So a 400 ton cumulus cloud, what dimensions?
So that would be of the order of a sort of cubic kilometer
or something like that, one and a half kilometers cubic.
That's a sort of typical size of a cumulus cloud.
But of course the gravity isn't acting
on the cloud as a whole.
It's acting on the individual tiny little droplets,
which are of the order of few thousandth
of a millimeter across within the cloud.
And so actually they only fall very, very slowly,
perhaps a centimeter per second or something like that.
And you actually have motion within the cloud,
upward motion, which sort of basically sustains
the altitude of those droplets.
So they don't just drop out and fall down.
They collide and coalesce with each other.
They join up and become bigger droplets.
And eventually once they're heavy enough,
they can actually fall out and become precipitation.
This is the magic of clouds,
comes from the special nature of water
that's naturally found in the three states
of solid, liquid and gas.
And that is really the secret of this kind of poetic
and beautiful quality of clouds
because they can appear and disappear at will
because one of those states, the gas one is invisible.
And so we're at the triple point of these three states
on earth in the atmosphere of earth.
And so the clouds are revealing the changes,
revealing the invisible movements of the air.
These movements of the winds are happening the whole time.
We only see them when they just nudge that water
to shift state from the gas form we can't see
to the liquid or the solid.
That's a very beautiful thought actually
is that they make the atmosphere visible.
They're the face of the atmosphere.
They're expressions on the face of the atmosphere.
And so they can reveal the moods,
the shifting, ever shifting moods of the atmosphere.
And we just intrinsically know how to read those moods.
Ask a child when they see a cloud that is dark
with a base that's low
and they know what's going to happen.
They know that that's very likely to produce rain.
You know, we've always known that right back to,
I imagine, you know, when we were living in caves.
Now we know the science of it.
We know why,
but they've always been this shifting expression
on the atmosphere that, you know,
I think we need to be more in tune with.
I think it is good for the mental health
and your well-being to be engaged with the sky personally.
What is it?
What's the physics of that?
So why are rain clouds dark?
First of all, I mean, clouds look white,
most of them, liquid clouds look white
because they're scattering the incoming radiation
that's coming from the sun.
And they scatter that radiation quite equally
across different wavelengths of light.
And that's why they look white.
Often if you see a kind of gray cloud,
it's sometimes a shadowing effect.
So it's kind of the cloud's own shadow.
So if it's a very large kind of low cloud, as you said,
it's basically kind of shadowing
and you can't see that scattering effect as well.
How bright they look is sort of dependent
on how they're made.
So if you have lots of small little droplets
within the cloud,
then it is very good at scattering that light.
It will look very bright and very white.
As the droplets grow and become larger,
then it sort of becomes less effective at the scattering.
And it's the tallness of the cloud
that's super important when it comes to a dark base
because a cloud that's tall has a dark base
because it just, the light doesn't really get through.
And a cloud that's tall is much more likely
to produce precipitation
because it often starts with the droplets
starting to freeze at the top.
It starts as snow, melts on the way down,
maybe lands as rain,
but that tallness is crucial to a lot of precipitation.
One of the things that I love about clouds as well,
you know, you mentioned there about how they appear white
because they scatter the wavelengths of color,
but Rayleigh scattering,
which is what makes the sky blue
because the sky isn't physically blue
because at nighttime you can see through it
up to the stars, right?
And then in the morning,
when the sun is lower in the sky
and the light is sort of grazing the atmosphere of the earth,
those wavelengths are scattered again
and you get more of the reds coming through
because the red wavelength is kind of,
could we describe it a bit like a wibbly wobbly wave?
Is that right?
Has that ever been said before?
Just a wave, Brian, yeah.
I didn't need to unnecessarily add wibbly wobbly then.
There's no un-wibbly wobbly wave.
It's a bit of superfluous.
Someone was saying that this one was wibblier and wobblier
and I think the wibblier wobbliness of this is that.
Does he mean the amplitude or the frequency?
No, I mean the wibbly wobbliness.
I think it's a longer wave, yeah.
It's a longer wave, there we go.
So it is more wibbly and less wobbly?
No, it's more wobbly and less wibbly, all right.
Brian, I know you've got a question for everyone
because as usual last Tuesday,
you were with Gloria Estefan and the Miami Sound Machine.
I was on the radio with,
and it was Gloria Estefan and Bob Mortimer.
Just duetting as usual.
And Bob Mortimer said,
so I have a question, a question.
I said, what is it?
And he said, you know if you get a crisp packet
and you open it and you eat all the crisps on an aeroplane
and then open the aeroplane window
and drop the crisp packet and it falls onto a cloud,
will it sit there on the top of the cloud?
Can I just mention, by the way,
if you are an aeroplane, please don't open the window.
If you're an assessor, you'll be all right.
But I had to think for a moment.
I thought that's quite a nice question.
So what was your answer then?
Let's find out if Brian's answer is right.
To tell you about our mushroom Swiss grill burger
at Dairy Queen, we've taken an actual conversation
overheard at a DQ restaurant between two brothers
and purely for your entertainment,
made it sound like a badly acted Kung Fu movie.
Hey Stevie, can I have a bite
of your mushroom Swiss grill burger?
No, please.
No, pretty please.
No, pretty, pretty please.
No.
Mom, Billy took my burger.
No, it's my grill burger.
Ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha ha.
The DQ mushroom Swiss grill burger
featuring real Swiss cheese, mouth-watering mushrooms
and mild garlic mayo.
One of six from the new grill burger menu.
Do one today and DQ something different
at participating DQ restaurants.
So, I mean, they look so crisp,
especially when you're in a plane
and when the cumulus clouds are below you,
but like you have that kind of boundary
in between what cloud and not.
It looks solid, doesn't it?
Yeah, it looks solid.
But then when you fly through those,
you see it's just like, you know,
flying through a cloud of smoke
or like, you know, fried fish.
It's like, it's like a cloud of smoke.
It's like a cloud of smoke.
It's like, you know, Friday night at my house
when I've got the dry ice on.
So I think the, which the cat despises.
I love that, the dry ice.
Is that what it is?
Like, put the dry ice on.
I think it would, it would fall through it.
Yeah, I came to the conclusion that it would fall through.
So it's a good physics question.
Yeah, the layer right at the top of the cloud
is often quite turbulent because the clouds emit radiation.
And so that can actually drive motions
along the tops of the clouds.
So I actually think it would probably get transported
around by the air currents,
rather than being held up
by the water droplets of the cloud.
I think the actual turbulent motion,
this sort of mixing effect at the top of the clouds
because the clouds are emitting radiation
out towards space would probably hold it up.
Are you saying it would move
in a wibbly wobbly fashion?
A wibbly wobbly fashion.
He thought he was being,
I think he just thought he was being Bob Morton,
but it's actually a really good physics question,
isn't it?
Because as you said, I didn't think of that actually,
the radiation back out again.
Is that one of the reasons you feel turbulence
when you enter clouds in an aircraft?
Yeah, well, that's exactly what you're experiencing.
All of those upward motions I described before
that are happening,
all of the local currents that are happening
within the cloud is basically what causes
that turbulence for the aircraft.
The top of the cloud in particular,
because you've basically got a body
which is emitting radiation,
emitting thermal radiation,
and that's dependent on the temperature
at the top of the cloud, basically.
So how cold the top of the cloud is determines
how much energy it's going to emit out.
Is it always hotter at a higher temperature
than the air, the clear air above it?
Depends on if it's an unstable atmosphere,
because in a stable atmosphere,
a thermal might rise from the ground and come back down
because it's not warmer than the surrounding atmosphere.
And you don't have clouds forming or storms developing,
but in an unstable atmosphere, as we describe it,
the air gets more rapidly cold as you go up.
And therefore, if you lift some air
from near the ground where it's warm,
it comes up, some droplets begin to form as it cools.
And remember, every time a tiny droplet forms,
a little bit of heat is released,
the latent heat as it changes state.
And those all add up,
even though it's a tiny amount from each tiny droplet.
And this is like fuel to keep the buoyancy
in an unstable atmosphere.
So the droplets form, it gets more buoyant,
more droplets form, it gets more buoyant,
and you get building, building, building
to this enormous cathedral of clouds
that is the cumulonimbus storm cloud.
And within that, these currents,
vertical currents are rising rapidly in some areas,
precipitation's falling fast in other areas,
and sometimes hailstones develop
because these particles are going round and round
and building up in layers of ice.
So Bob Mortimer's crisp packet
could have ended up in the middle of a hailstone.
It's gonna be one of those very famous physics examples
that all undergraduates learn in atmospheric physics,
isn't it?
Mortimer's crisp packet.
That was the infinite monkey cage, you know?
But just to pick up on that point,
because it's an interesting bit of physics,
the fact that water droplets forming release energy.
Could you just maybe, Amanda, just speak about that?
Yeah, so going back to Gavin's triple point for water,
so any time that water changes phase,
so whether it goes from a gas to a liquid
or from a liquid to a solid,
in that direction, it's, yeah,
basically releasing a little bit of energy,
which is to do with the organisation
of the water molecules, basically, within the structure.
So once it condenses and it turns to a liquid,
that little bit of energy gets released.
And as Gavin said,
that contributes to a heating in the atmosphere.
It's basically this latent heating effect of the clouds
as they're forming.
And you get the opposite as well.
So you could have ice crystals up at the top
of one of these cumulonimbus clouds.
They spread out in an anvil,
this enormous plume of ice crystals.
It spreads out hundreds and hundreds of miles.
And in one area, those ice crystals can melt
and therefore change state in the other way.
That makes the air cool a bit.
And you can get these sinking pockets
that appear as mama clouds on the underside,
these pouches of cloud on the underside
of one of these cumulonimbus anvil plumes.
And they look really distinctive,
these pouches of clouds.
And they're the result of the cooling,
most likely, it's not totally understandable,
most likely the result of the cooling that happens
with the shift in state the other way.
We've all seen those, haven't we, those anvil clouds.
Why are they so flat at the top of the cloud?
So going back to what Gavin talked about
with the stability of the atmosphere.
So particularly in the tropics,
we find a lot of these deep cumulonimbus clouds
over the warm tropical oceans.
There's a huge amount of fuel and moisture
which allows these clouds to get up
to altitudes of 18 or 19 kilometers.
This is sort of almost twice the height
of cruise altitudes of typical aircraft.
So these are really tall clouds.
And what happens is you hit a sort of boundary,
we call it the tropopause.
It's basically the transition
between the lower part of the atmosphere
where all of our weather happens and the clouds form
and the layer above it, which is called the stratosphere.
And it's called stratosphere because it's stratified layer.
It's a stable layer.
And so the clouds basically get up to this,
it's almost like a lid.
They can't move above that because the air above is stable.
And so they can only spread out.
And that's why you get these anvil clouds
because they then just spread sideways
because they can't travel further upwards anymore.
And if you see the photographs from the space station
where one of the astronauts takes a photo down
onto cumulonimbus clouds,
it's like they've formed underneath a piece of glass.
There's this temperature profile,
this temperature inversion, we call it,
because it's the opposite of the normal
getting colder as you go up.
It starts to get warmer at the top of the troposphere.
And that's this invisible lid
and the cloud you can just see spread out.
And it just can't go up any, it wants to go up higher,
but it can't go up any higher
because it suddenly gets stable there.
This is another incredible thing about clouds
is how you get so many different kind of shapes
and reasons as why things look a certain way
or are a certain way.
And they've intrigued people forever.
And I suppose it's only fairly recently
that we as people have kind of fully been able to understand
what these things are and why they're doing those things.
I was going to ask that question actually
about the, in terms of the physics of the atmosphere,
what's the history of the scientific understanding
of the physics of the atmosphere?
How recently did we begin to get a good picture
of what's happening?
In terms of the modern understanding of the atmosphere.
So in the sort of 17, 1800s,
when people were getting into sort of ballooning
in a big way and starting to try
and leave the surface of the earth
and with them were taking some instruments
to sort of measure temperature and pressure
and trying to really understand
what the vertical structure of the atmosphere is.
That was really the first time that we started to get
some of this basic information
about temperature decreasing with height
as you go through the troposphere,
pressure decreasing with height.
So that was a sort of, those were really key foundations.
I think in the more modern era,
the advances in technologies we've had,
the ability to measure through things like radars, lidars,
through satellite measurements with radiometers,
that's really given us a much more global view.
Aircraft measurements, flying through clouds
and actually measuring these droplets.
How big are they?
How many of them are there?
What's sitting in the nucleus
of those little droplets and things?
All of those technologies
in the last sort of 50 or 60 years probably
has really revolutionized our understanding.
Oh, and I just wanted to go back to
when you were mentioning ice crystals.
I remember the first time of looking up in the sky
and seeing the kind of the, I don't know what the,
it's like a cloud bow, is it called?
I'm not sure what it's called.
Oh yeah, yes, you're kind of the iridescent clouds
or the, when you see those gorgeous colours in a cloud
they are incredible to see because it's like a rainbow
but it's more kind of localized, I suppose,
in the same way as you get sun dogs,
which is like a kind of a halo,
which can appear on the sun or a moon or the moon rather.
It's the sort of prism effect of,
I think I'm right in saying this,
of the ice crystals or the water droplets rather,
which scatters the spectrum.
And then you get these amazing patches of colour in the sky.
That's one thing that people love taking photos of as well
because it just looks that kind of iridescence,
you know, that you see.
We don't see that every day when we look up at the sky.
So whenever you see something like that,
you want to go, wow, I want to take a photo of that.
And if your phone's anything like mine,
the photo will look absolutely rubbish then
and you'll just delete it.
Yeah, the only one that works better,
like if you try and do a rainbow or anything like that,
it's never as good.
But Aurora Borealis, you just look at a black sky
but you stick it through a camera and go,
it looks like I saw something amazing, didn't it?
The sky's a cheat, isn't it, Brian?
But we'll deal with that another day.
On the subject of sort of beautiful optical effects,
we're talking mainly about clouds forming
within this troposphere,
the lowest layer of the atmosphere,
but actually you can get clouds even higher than that.
So there are types of clouds called noctilucent clouds
that form very high up,
about 80 kilometres above the surface.
It's very, very dry up in the mesosphere,
but it's very, very cold.
It's about minus 120 degrees Celsius there.
So even though it's very dry,
it gets cold enough that you can still form
these very, very thin ice clouds.
And you can see those sometimes if you're lucky,
particularly at sort of dusk or in the morning
when you get that, as Owen was describing,
you get this sort of horizontal path of the light
through the atmosphere,
which gives you that sort of reddy colours.
You can sort of see them, very like ghost-like clouds almost.
Similarly, in the stratosphere,
we have these mother-of-pearl clouds,
they're often called, the nacreous clouds,
which again form over the polar regions
where it's very, very cold.
And again, you can get these beautiful effects,
like light effects, if you're lucky enough to see those.
Gavin, I wondered about, you know,
having done, having, you know,
Cloudspotter's Guide and things like that,
which is when Amanda was talking earlier on
about the importance of, you know,
what we might call imperfections or grey, whatever,
if you had written that book
and put that together in 1950, for instance,
what were the different formations we might've seen,
thinking of the nature of injury,
thinking of the nature of the smog in London,
all of those things,
where we wouldn't have seen so many condensation trails
that form behind aircraft.
I mean, I guess there were,
there weren't, just weren't so many of those.
And those are human-made clouds
that result from the water vapour
in the exhaust of the aircraft,
cooling as it rapidly expands in the high atmosphere
and forming this crisp line of cloud.
So long as that part of the atmosphere
that the plane's flying through
has enough moisture in it anyway,
otherwise it doesn't form.
It's a bit like when you start your car on a cold day,
you can see kind of the plumes of moisture
that are in amongst all the other exhaust fumes of your car,
but you don't see them on a dry, warm day.
But yeah, we have,
we would have had far more particulates
from all the cold smoke and pollution
that was in particulate form.
And those have an effect on the fog.
You get lots and lots of tiny droplets
if you've got lots and lots of these little aerosols
for the droplets to get started on.
And that's a thick, dense, nasty fog,
the Pease Super that, you know, London was known for,
which is especially nasty
because it has pollution at its centre.
So clouds would have been different in some ways,
but the main formations, I think,
have been the same forever.
We've talked about weather,
but can we now talk about climate?
What role do the clouds play in climate modelling?
So the clouds have a really important effect
on the balance of energy of our planet.
So they do two main things.
We talked earlier on about the scattering by clouds
of the incoming radiation from the sun.
So that has the effect of cooling the planet.
So less of that sun,
solar radiation reaches the surface of the earth
and causes heating.
So that's a cooling effect,
but they also can contribute to warming,
particularly the higher altitude clouds,
which are colder.
We talked about the clouds themselves
emitting their own radiation, their own thermal energy,
and they therefore have a sort of trapping effect
and can contribute to heating of the planet.
So the overall effect that they have on the climate
is the balance between two opposing effects,
this cooling effect and the warming effect.
Now in the current day,
the net of those two things
is that the clouds contribute to a cooling of the climate.
So if we did a sort of thought experiment
and got rid of all the clouds on the planet
and thought about what that would mean for our climate,
roughly we'd expect the temperature
to be about 10 degrees warmer at the surface
than without the clouds.
So it's quite a significant effect.
So the average global temperature.
The average temperature, yes,
would be significantly warmer
if we didn't have that cooling effect.
So they're absolutely critical for the climate.
A really important question is, of course,
what's happening to clouds now that the planet is warming
and the atmosphere is becoming warmer.
And so the big question is,
which of those two competing effects will win out
in terms of whether the cloud changes
might amplify the warming of the planet
that's occurring due to greenhouse gas increases
or whether they might offset it.
So at the moment, basically the science evidence as it is,
we think that the clouds will contribute to further warming.
So they'll basically amplify the global warming
that's coming from the greenhouse gas increases
in the atmosphere.
And it's a sort of positive feedback effect in that way.
Clouds drive climate scientists crazy, don't they?
Because they mess up their computer models.
They're so dynamic and the system is so complex
that you only need a slight change in the clouds
and then fast forward your model 50 years.
And it's entirely different
from if the clouds did something else.
So you've got this really complex role
that the clouds play in temperatures down in the ground.
High ones have a warming effect.
Low ones have a cooling effect.
And then this change in clouds that seems to be emerging,
you know, we've had studies look at how clouds have changed
over 24 years of consistent satellite data.
And you start to see fewer of those low cooling clouds
in the cloudier regions of our planet.
And these are sort of worrying signs
that the clouds may be shifting
and that shift may have a feedback loop.
What of the uncertainties,
the major uncertainties in climate models?
Our understanding of cloud,
is that one of the bigger problems
that we have in the models?
It's the biggest source of uncertainty
that we have as climate scientists
in being able to kind of quantify
how much warmer the planet might be
in sort of 50 years from now, for example.
So we're very, very confident
that as greenhouse gases increase in the atmosphere,
the planet will warm.
But exactly by how much is more difficult
because of these feedback loops that start to kick in
as the atmosphere is warming and clouds are really tricky.
As Gavin said, we need to use computer models
to make projections and predictions into the future.
And so we're solving lots of complicated equations
on big supercomputers,
but the scales of the clouds, as we've been discussing,
are absolutely microscopic.
You're talking about droplets, you know,
of the size of a few thousandth of a millimetre,
you know, and you need to then represent that
at a global scale.
So it's a real challenge.
And what we need to do in our models
is kind of use physics to enable us
to represent those small scale processes
across a larger area.
We're in a really exciting time now, I think,
where we're able to have enough computer power
where we can actually start to resolve
finer and finer spatial scales
and we can actually run computer models, you know,
with scales of the orders of tens of metres
rather than, you know, hundreds of kilometres.
And at those scales,
you're really then explicitly representing
all of that physics in the model,
the microphysics and the interactions
of the droplets with the little particles and so on
is all being simulated by the model.
And you start to see really interesting things
happening then, like convective organisation, for example,
where clouds, little pockets of cloud
actually through their own circulations
will draw together and become a larger cloud system
and turn into a mesoscale convective system, for example,
one of these bigger storm clouds by themselves.
We've only got time for one more question
and your favourite question this week, Brian,
which we've not got to, but you were very excited by this,
is balloons, how do they work?
Now, this is true, by the way, I'm not making this up.
It wasn't my favourite, I read it.
Well, your favourite one was the crisp one,
but that's what makes it next to your celebrity.
I read it in the script and said,
that is an absolutely ridiculous question,
why would that be there?
No, you didn't, you went, it's true.
How do they work?
Have you segwayed from a discussion
about the detail of the climate
so that balloons were on the back?
I'll tell you why, because we've only got a minute left,
so we can continue quickly or we could just go,
so, Owain, I know that balloons have played a major part
in your fascination with...
Absolutely, I mean, there's the Peppa Pig balloon,
aforementioned, but also, when I was about four,
a weather balloon crashed into our garden in Ammanford,
which is in South West Wales, where I grew up,
and I remember this thing, my father going out
and sort of saying to my older brother,
oh, this thing's in the garden, and I was tiny,
but I can remember this weather balloon in the garden,
and it looked like a big polystyrene box
with some sort of material attached to it,
and apparently I went up to it and I gave it a good kick,
and that was my introduction to weather forecasting,
I think, and all these years later,
who'd have thought that I would still be interested
in what weather balloons
and what weather forecasting systems do
after that first kick?
Just think, if you'd really had been a little bit smarter,
you could have turned that into the Roswell of South Wales.
Oh, my gosh.
You could have turned that into, yeah.
Well, you know what, you walk around some parts
of that town and it looks,
it feels like we're in Roswell, 1947.
We asked the audience a question.
We always have fabulous minds here.
So the question we asked the audience was,
what's the strangest thing a cloud has reminded you of?
This is a good one.
It reminded me that I'd forgotten the tent.
All right, what have you got?
This is from Daniel.
I love this one.
The strangest thing a cloud has reminded you of?
It's probably time to open my parachute.
Yeah, I think so, Daniel.
A heavy Dora Storm cloud reminded me of John McEnroe
because I knew it could not be Cirrus.
I'm just like, it's very,
I don't know if I can read that.
I think it says, but it can't say this, can it?
What's the strangest thing a cloud has reminded you of?
A tiny fluffy fruit bat growing on a digestive.
I think that's what it says.
No, it doesn't.
Gnawing.
Gnawing on a, oh, now it makes sense.
This is lovely.
This is from Niamh.
My granddad, not because he was strange,
but because he would get a spoon out
on cloudy days to eat them.
I believed him.
That's like Cosmic Comicus.
I love that one.
Oh, that's brilliant.
Well, thank you very much.
Thanks to our panel,
who were Professor Amanda Maycock, Gavin Pretor-Pinney,
and Owen Wynne-Evans.
Thank you.
Next week, the infinite monkey cage
finally goes deep into the darkest recesses
of the monkey cage,
because we are considering the sex life of monkeys.
And if you've ever seen monkeys,
you don't have to go into the darkest recesses.
They do it everywhere.
Thank you very much, everyone.
We'll see you again.
Bye-bye.
♪ Infinite monkey cage ♪
Till now, nice again.
Hi, I'm Phil Wang,
and this is a podcast to podcast trailer
for a different podcast than this podcast
that you've listened to or are going to listen to.
But nonetheless, I'm talking about another podcast
that you should also definitely listen to.
The podcast I'm talking about is Comedy of the Week,
which takes choice episodes from BBC sitcoms,
sketch shows, podcasts, and panel shows,
including my own show, Unspeakable,
and puts them all into one podcast.
Maybe I'll trail this podcast on that podcast.
Who's to say?
I'll do what I like.
Listen to Comedy of the Week now on BBC Sounds.
Podcast.